<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!DOCTYPE properties SYSTEM "http://java.sun.com/dtd/properties.dtd">

<properties>
  <entry key="helpChangeAdd"><![CDATA[
The change-add command adds a change to the currently open release.
The command will fail if the release is not open for modification.
Releases are opened for modification with the release-begin command,
and closed for modification with the release-finish command.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpInitialize"><![CDATA[
The initialize command initializes an empty changelog.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpWritePlain"><![CDATA[
The write-plain command produces a humanly-readable plain text version
of the changelog. Various options can be specified to control which
entries are displayed, and how they are formatted.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpWriteXHTML"><![CDATA[
The write-xhtml command produces an XHTML version of the changelog.
Various options can be specified to control which entries are
displayed, and how they are formatted.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpWriteAtom"><![CDATA[
The write-atom command produces an Atom RSS feed of the changelog.
Various options can be specified to control which entries are
displayed, and how they are formatted.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpReleaseBegin"><![CDATA[
The release-begin command attempts to add a new open release to the changelog.
The created release is open for modification such that subsequent uses of the
change-add command will successfully add changes to the release. If the --version
option is not used, a sensible version number will be generated based on the
previous release (if any).
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpReleaseFinish"><![CDATA[
The release-finish command attempts to close the most recent open release
present in the changelog, or a specific release if the --version option is
specified. The target release is closed for modification such that subsequent
uses of the change-add command targeting this release will fail.
]]></entry>

  <entry key="helpReleaseSetVersion"><![CDATA[
The release-set-version command attempts to set the version number of the
currently open release.
]]></entry>

</properties>
